Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 7 -- Letters to Franklin 1783 January-November Mss.B.F85inventory07
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 1; L.S. 2p.; Boyer, -----. Bordeaux
    Desires to establish a glass-works in America; willing to undertake the expense if Congress will accord him all the privileges and facilities in their power.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Lotbinière, Michel-Alain Chartier de. Paris
    His delight at America's independence; disappointed that Canada was not united as a fourteenth province; indignant at the boundary line being drawn at Lat. 41° N.; explains the value to America of the Great Lakes and Lake Champlain; desires an interview on the subject with Franklin and Adams. Lands he owns near Crown Point, extending to Lake George and including Ticonderoga; hopes Franklin will uphold these claims before Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Ridley, Matthew. Paris
    Enclosing the power of attorney to be certified; dictates a simple form which he can use.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 3; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Vaughan, Samuel Jr. Paris
    Desires Franklin to forward any letters addressed to Miss Laurens to his care; accident which delayed the party's journey to London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Feron, -----. Vernon
    Desires Franklin at least to indicate the cheapest route to America, as well as the most temperate climate in which to settle.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 3; A.L.S. 4p.; Coulougnac and Co. Nantes
    Debt owing them by the State of Virginia through the agency of M. Penct; encloses a memoir [2p.] which will give him an exact idea of the entire transaction; begs him to appoint a commission to look into their titles; much further delay in the payment of this sum will result in their ruin; will suspend all legal proceedings until they hear his decision in the matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Loyseau, -----. Paris
    Interested in a steel-works near Paris; desires to know if there is any market for this product in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Jay, Mr. and Mrs. John
    Inviting him to dinner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 3; L.S. 1p.; Fizeaux, Grand and Co. Amsterdam
    Mr. [Robert] Morris's bill was paid and another was drawn on Dr. Franklin for their reimbursement.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 4; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Houdetot, Comtesse d'
    Regrets that she must see Franklin eight days later than she had expected.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 4; A.L.S. 3p.; Stourm, Jean-Louis. Bellfort
    Congratulations on the independence of America. Sends an essay of his, entitled "Le Royaume Imaginaire."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 4; A.L.S. 3p.; Connelly and Sons and Arthur. Dunkirk
    Account of their firm; desires him to recommend them to some good houses at Boston, Charleston, Philadelphia and New York, and to appoint Philip or Joseph Connelly Consul at Dunkirk.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Lenoble, Capt ----- de. Hanau
    Spent a considerable time in America and desires to return there and enter army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Campo-de-Arbe, ------. Paris
    Begs for recommendations among Franklin's acquaintance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Brossière, ------. L'Orient
    Desiring information concerning M. Loch, whether his present wife is living and when the marriage took place; one of his parishioners, Mlle. Desbois, thought for a long time to be the wife of M. Loch, denies this fact and is desirous of accepting an offer of marriage; cannot perform the ceremony until he receives the desired information.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Walker, George. Calais
    Congratulates him on the declaration of peace. Introduced himself to Mr. Oswald on his passage through Calais and asked him England's intentions as regarded the ruined planters of Barbadoes; expects no redress of a public nature and despairs of even a private one; wishes to be put in the way of earning a livelihood.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 6; L.S. 2p.; Vergennes, Charles Gravier, comte de. Versailles
    Concerning the loan of six millions of livres which the king proposes to grant to Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 6; A.L.S. 4p.; Ostervald, Frédéric-Samuel. Neufchatel
    He and his associates are the founders and directors of a printing house; liberty of the press enjoyed in Switzerland; begs Franklin to recommend his firm to the leading libraries in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Defay, Mlle ----. Paris
    Congratulates him on the peace. Begs him to accede to the prayers of M. Gastellier.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 7; L.S. 1p.; Vergennes, Charles Gravier, comte de. Versailles
    Sends him a copy of a letter just received from le Marquis de Castrics [2p.], narrating the indecent manner in which four distinguished French officers were treated by Capt. Thomas Smith of the privateer, "General Garveret"; hopes Franklin will use his authority to punish the offenders.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 7; A.L.S. 4p.; Backhaus, Jean Guillaume. Hanover
    Proposes a German regiment for the use of America and to recruit it mainly from the Germans who will return from service in that country; the details of his plan; asks for Franklin's endorsement.
    A.E. by Dr. Franklin. The United States will probably not keep up a standing army; most of the Germans likely to settle in America rather than return to Europe; has no authority to set on foot the negotiations he suggests.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 7; A.L.S. 4p.; Delius, Christoph Diedrich Arnold. Bremen
    Has been established in Bremen for nearly twenty years and has dealt extensively in linen and other merchandise for exportation; his present intention to send a vessel laden with merchandise to Boston and to make the voyage himself as supercargo; begs for a letter of recommendation to the President of Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Lotbinière, Michel-Alain Chartier de. Paris
    The boundaries between the American and English possessions; expresses himself as quite satisfied. Reminds him of his promise to bring the affair of his American possessions to the notice of Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 8; A.L.S. 3p.; Byde, Thomas Plumer. Naples
    A member of the first Parliament of the present King of England where his name appears in the list of those who voted for the repeal of the Stamp Act; congratulates Franklin on the happy conclusion of the war. Desires the position of Consul in one of the ports of Italy. Begs him to forward the enclosed letter to Mr. Wharton.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 8; A.L.S. 3p.; Schuster, Jean Chrétien. Vienna
    Named his son Benjamin Silas Arthur in honor of Franklin and his colleagues, Deane and Lee. His attachement and admiration for Franklin and America. Desires the address of merchants at Boston, Philadelphia, New York and Charleston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Gastellier, René Georges
    Sends by the Marquis Dusaillant (son-in-law of the Marquis de Mirabeau) his little work dedicated to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Sends the rough draft of a French letter [2p.] which he has written for Franklin; feels that he failed to speak as befitted the liberator of America. Apologizes for not asking Franklin to dine with other members of the Lodge of the Nine Sisters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Ingraham and Bromfield. Bordeaux
    Desire to know whether it is necessary to have a particular passport for their vessel, which is about to sail for New England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Sazy, Guillaume. Fiume
    Begging Franklin to grant him the position of American Consul or Agent at any sea-port he may be pleased to name.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Loyseau, -----. Paris
    Presumes Franklin failed to receive his last letter, asking if there was any market for steel in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Bussy-Dagoneau, comte de. Chateau de Pierre Encize
    Sends him an ode on peace, also an account on himself [2p.], the reason for his present captivity and his hopeless state of health.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Linckh, Jean Bernard. Hirschberg
    Begs Franklin to recommend him to those American merchants who trade in linens.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 13; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Vaughan, Samuel Jr. Paris
    Accepting his invitation for dinner on Sunday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Amandeur, J François. Paris
    Desires to go to America. Is a watch maker.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 13; L. in 3d P. 1p.; MacMahon, John. At the Military school in Paris
    Will break a previous engagement to wait on him the following Sunday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 13; L.S. 1p.; Mailly, chevalier de. Paris
    Inquires if it is true that the United States grants large tracts of land on advantageous terms to those who will cultivate them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Mirabeau, marquis de. Paris
    Dr. Gastellier desires to know if Franklin will accept the dedication of his book; speaks in the highest terms of this physician.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 13; A.L.S. 3p.; De Vinck and Co. Ostend
    Desiring to send over several vessels to Boston or Philadelphia and form an establishment there; their agent in Philadelphia, Rodolph Tillier, obtained from Mr. Adams the best letters of recommendation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Siegmüller, Capt -----. Austria
    German by birth. Served in the Austrian army. Begs Franklin to procure him some suitable position in America.
    (In Latin.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Perret, -----. Nantes
    Sending him the proceedings relative to certain prizes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 14; L.S. 2p.; Ollivier and Others(Municipal Officers of Port Louis). Port Louis
    Desire to obtain for Port Louis the privilege of trading with the United States; they have written on this subject to the Marquis de Castries.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783 February 14]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Vaughan, Samuel Jr. Paris
    Enclosing a letter from Mr. [William] Hodgson. Lord Surr[e]y talked of as Ambassador to America. Report of Mr. [Henry] Laurens's intended arrival in Paris on the 11th inst.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, David
    Mr. Mace, Secretary to Mr. Murray during his Embassy to Constantinople, desires to be employed by the United States as Ambassador to the Porte, as Secretary to the Embassy, or Consul in Europe.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Bissy, Stefano, baron de. Bruges
    Enthuses over the establishment of peace and the crowning of Franklin's labors; wishes him a long life and happiness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Bryan, Arthur and William Jr. Dublin
    Requesting a passport for their ship which will be ready to sail in sixteen or eighteen days. Thinks it will be necessary for the commerce of the United States to have a Consul at Dublin; offer themselves.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Macarty, George William René. Vannes
    Has forgotten his father's address, so begs Franklin to forward him the enclosed letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 15; L.S. 3p.; Lalanne, -----. Bayonne
    Never doubted the success of America from the moment of her Treaty of Alliance with France. Advantages of the port of Bayonne as a center of trade with the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Lanoix, L. Bordeaux
    Wrote December 10th asking for a passport for his vessel "Le Grand d'Estaing"; imagines the peace will enable him to dispense with this precaution; wishes to know if an English passport is necessary.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 16; A.L.S. 12p.; Ortlieb, J.M. Reichenweyr, Upper Alsace
    Concerning the cultivation of the vine. Accompanied by a French essay on same subject, addressed to M. Joly de Fleury, Director-General of Finances.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 16; L.S. 2p.; John Torris and Wante. Dunkerque
    Reminding him of his promise to give them one of the hundred passports he expects from London together with a letter of recommendation for Messrs. Bache and Shee at Philadelphia; determined to hasten the departure of their vessel, the "Franklin," which only waits for the desired passport.
    A.E. by Dr. Franklin. Will make a letter of recommendation to Messrs. Bache and Shee and send it with the passport.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 17; A.L.S. 3p.; Schopman, -----. Anvers
    Desires to go to Philadelphia, Boston or Charleston, and Practise as an architect; begs Franklin to grant him a free passage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Fleury and Demadières. Orleans
    Sending a bill for the expenses incurred in forwarding various boxes to Dr. Franklin; desires to know whether a red box marked B.F., contents unknown, is intended for him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Price, M. Paris
    Begging Franklin to name her husband American Agent at Marseilles.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Roze de Chantoiseau, Mathurin
    Hopes Franklin will accept the work he sends; ardently desirous that his scheme for the liquidation of a state's debt may be of use to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Loyseau, -----
    Reason why he wrote Franklin regarding the means of exporting steel to America. Slanders against him by Mr. William Alexander; defends himself from such an attack. His high opinion of [Comte] de Benyowsky.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 17; L.S. 2p.; Westerwick, ----- and Friedrich Steyn. Paris
    His promise to grant them letters of recommendation to Boston and Philadelphia; they are about to go to America on business.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Woddrop, John. Glasgow
    Desires his opinion as to what merchandise of Ireland, Scotland and Great Britain will have the best chance of selling in America; mentions certain fabrics which will be in great demand during the summer season; if he needs a pass to ship these articles, begs Franklin to send him one.
  - to Thomas Morris, 1783 February 17; A.L.S. 4p.; Herman Heyman's Sons. Bremen
    Delighted at America's independence; their commercial relations with the United States; expect to send a vessel there in three weeks; their partners are Mr. Henry Talla and Mr. Arnold Delius; refers Franklin to the latter's letter of the 7th inst.; desire letters of introduction and recommendation, especially to Congress, in order that they may receive protection and consideration.
    A.E. by Dr. Franklin. The inhabitants of North America accustomed to treat strangers with hospitality and kindness; a recommendation to the Governor to protect them is neither necessary nor usual; encloses a letter to friends who will give Mr. Delins any advice a stranger may need.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Van de Perre, P.E. Marseilles
    Delighted at the approaching peace. Recommending M. Conclair for the position of Consul at Marseilles.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Buchan, David Stewart Eskine, Earl of, 1742-1829
    His desire to promote the emigration of certain of his countrymen to the United States.
    Bibliography
    Printed in Works (Sparks, IX, 486; Bigelow, VIII, 258).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Bertier, Père Joseph Etienne. Paris
    Offers to send him his history on the beginning of the world and of men, proved by the agreement between the laws of physics and the book of Genesis.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 19; A.L.S. 4p.; Valltravers, Johann Rodolph. Vienna
    Congratulating him on the glorious success of all his labors; offers various suggestions which he believes will be of use to the United States; will procure all these advantages for America as soon as he is authorized to do so by Congress. Presents the application of an old friend of his, an eminent surveyor and engineer, who desires a commission from Congress to employ his squadron of four ships on a voyage of discovery on their behalf; what he would require of Congress in return for his services.
    (In duplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Counèler, Laurent. Marseilles
    Asking for the position of Consul at Marseilles.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 19; A.L.S. 3p.; Lynen le jeune, Isaac. Stolberg
    Interested in the manufacture of various articles in brass; inquires if there is any market for these wares in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Weinbrenner, Joseph Paul Reichsfreiherr von. Vienna
    Desiring Franklin to furnish him with the names of various reliable firms in Boston, Philadelphia and New york with which they may enter into commercial relations.
    (In French. In duplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Pomaret, Jean Gal. Ganges
    Enclosing a letter for Miss Laurens. Recommends M. Marc-Antoine Bazile for the position of Consul at Languedoc.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Ruellan de Gallinée, J-Fr
    Concerning certain bills of exchange paid by the State of South Carolina in exchange for certain goods sent to Charleston; desires to know the value in French money of these bills.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Fottrell, John. Ostend
    Desires his opinion as to the advisability of sending to America any goods of English manufacture; asks for a pass which will insure their safety on arrival. Requested by the Chief Magistrates of Ostend to inform Franklin that every encouragement and facility will be granted to American trade in Belgium.
    A.E. by Dr. Franklin. Cannot advise him to send any British goods to America till he hears that the trade is open; acknowledging his offers of services and glad to hear of the Magistrates' good will.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Barry, Amelia. Pisa
    Congratulating him on the decision of the late contest, and wishing him all future prosperity and happiness. The severity of her fortune will never permit of her returning to England. Acknowledging Franklin's kindness in honoring her recommendation of Dr. and Miss Burrows; heard from the latter that Franklin mentioned his intention of sending her a sufficient sum to enable her to take her little helpless family to England; fears his letter on this subject may have miscarried; however, does not wish to solicit pecuniary favors; is accustomed to poverty herself and only worries about the future of her children.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 21; L.S. 3p.; Triol, Roux and Co. Marseilles
    The manner in which the Captain of their vessel had been obliged to make very disadvantageous terms after selling his cargo; thinks now that peace is declared and things readjusted, some compensation is due them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Price, M. Paris
    Reminds Franklin of her request for a Consulship for her husband; begs him to write to Congress on the subject; applies to him as she would to her father.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Wright, Patience. London
    Has just made up her packet for America, which goes by a faithful servant of Governor Franklin's; present address of the Governor; his work on behalf of the Tories; his health bad and he looks old. News of her own son Joseph being cast away near Boston in the ship "Argo." Hopes to see Franklin in Philadelphia that summer. Her righteous indignation at the Parliament in England; they adopt the faults of George and Charlotte. Great reception which Franklin would meet with if he came to London. Messages to his grandson. All the wise and prudent wait for the season to set out for America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Vivier, L. La Rochelle
    Is about to send a vessel to Chesapeake Bay for purposes of trade; if it is necessary to have a passport in order to unload his cargo, begs Franklin to send him one.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Enclosing a letter from [Tristram] Dalton, of Newburyport, asking for a larger allowance from Government for the brig "Fair Play."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Dufour, Madame. Paris
    Her husband is a master tailor and is unable to pay his debts; her child of fourteen months often wants the necessaries of life; begs Franklin to arrange for them to go to America where she and her husband can find work.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Grand de Castelle, -----. Dunkirk
    Offering his services as American Consul at Dunkirk.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 25; A.L.S. 8p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. London
    Terms of the peace not approved in England. His sympathy with England's present principles and his belief in the ultimate improvement of those who remain in office. Expects Franklin to visit him in London; has his apartments all prepared. Asks for a letter on behalf of Mr. Joshua Grigby, Jr., who, notwithstanding his considerable advantages of birth and fortune, intends going out to settle in America. Requests a second letter for Mr. John Darby, a relative of his own and Admiral Darby; will be very angry if Johnson did not get the Philosophical books Franklin wanted. Jack Lee execrates the peace and talks of "our fine fleet." Report that Franklin abuses England as much as ever he did during the war; his answer to all such accusations.
    Printed, in part, in Works (Sparks, IX, 489; Bigelow, VIII, 261).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 25; D.S. 4p.; Froger de Larigaudière, -----
    The advantages to the United States of having a free trading port in the Province of Saintonge, France; location of the port of Oleron in said province, near the town of Marennes, and its natural advantages and facilities for trade; offers to give his services free to the United States as Consul at the said port and town.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 25; A.L.S. Verses. 4p.; Bellujeu, Count de [?]. Champlitte
    Sends Dr. Franklin a military song in honor of King Louis, Washington and Franklin and requests the latter to forward a medal of Henri IV of France to General Washington.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 25; A.L.S. 4p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Complains at having been made to pay £23 for a pass for his ship "Mary"; consults Franklin about the advisability of sending their cargo before a Treaty of Commerce is settled; loss which a delay will mean to them; suggests that a letter to Congress in their favor might do away with any danger of seizure or confiscation. State of English politics; the Shelburnites completely routed; thinks this will make no difference to America; Lord Shelburne's lack of friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 26; A.L.S. 4p.; Ingenhousz, Jan